# **NICOLAS W. MALONGA**

347.984.2394 • nicolas.malonga@gmail.com www.linkedin.com/in/nicolasmalonga • www.malonganicolas.com

#### **SUMMARY**

Data Science and Analytics professional competent at modeling trends in large datasets and translating them into practical business solutions. MBA and Master's in Business Analytics graduate with engineering background and strong ability to combine project management experience and problem-solving abilities. Extensive global experience and cultural awareness with fluency in French and Portuguese. Successfully completed 2 years of Peace Corps volunteer service as a secondary school teacher in Mozambique.

#### **CORE COMPETENCIES**

Statistical Analysis and Programming in R and Python • Data Extraction, Transformation and Loading (ETL) • R Shiny Application Development • Descriptive and Predictive Machine Learning Modeling • Text Analytics • Big Data Mining and Visualization • Report Development and Automation • Project Management

## **EDUCATION**

# UNIVERSITY OF IOWA | Tippie School of Business, Iowa City, IA

Master of Science in Business Analytics, 2019 Master of Business Administration (M.B.A), 2018

CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK (CUNY) | City College of New York (CCNY), New York, NY

Bachelor of Engineering in Chemical Engineering, 2008

## **DATA SCIENCE & ANALYTICS PROJECTS**

- Stock Portfolio Optimization and Seasonality Analysis | R and R Shiny
- Supply Chain Risk Resiliency Assessment and Reporting | PySpark, R, R Shiny
- Topic Classification | Text Analytics and Classification using PySpark, Python, Keras
- Monthly Demand Forecasting Tool | Linear Regression, Hypothesis Testing using R, R Shiny
- License Registration Suspension Prediction | Random Forrest and Linear Regression using R
- Chemical Approval Process Standardization and Digitalization | SharePoint, Power Automate, MS Forms
- Loan Default Prediction | KNN, SVM, Decision Tree and Logistic Regression using R, Python, DataRobot

## **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

#### JOHN DEERE, Moline, IL | Data Scientist, EHS

SEPT 2021 - PRESENT

- Work within John Deere's Environmental, Health & Safety (EHS) unit to design, launch and manage a portfolio of data science and analytics projects focused on Technology & Digital Transformation.
- Support factories with limited data science and analytics capabilities by identifying and designing Business Intelligence tools that meet their needs and serving as the project manager to implement and promote them.

## JOHN DEERE, Moline, IL | Data Scientist, Data Science Enablement

JUN 2021 - SEPT 2021

- Worked within Data Science Enablement team to assist Supply Chain Management with its Analytics needs.
- Used an Agile approach to deliver high value analytics tools and solutions for a cross-functional audience.
   Achievement: Led the conception, development and deployment of an R Shiny application intended to automate risk resiliency assessment and reporting of John Deere's supply chain.

#### JOHN DEERE, Moline, IL | Data Scientist, Order Fulfillment

JUN 2020 - JUN 2021

- Supported Order Fulfillment in the development and maintenance of complex statistical models and predictive analytics solutions designed to improve forecasting of product demand, shipments and inventory.
- Built and maintained customer-facing visualization tools using Excel, Tableau and R Shiny to present forecast insights and metrics to both a technical and non-technical audience.
   Achievement: Developed an R Shiny application to forecast product demand. The tool incorporated

hypothesis testing to properly aggregate the data and linear regression to build the forecast models.

## JOHN DEERE, Olathe, KS | Data Scientist, Enterprise Market Research

JUN 2019 - JUN 2020

- Supported John Deere's Enterprise Market Research (EMR) unit by carrying out data science and analytics
  driven tasks to generate market insights that helped stakeholders make informed business decisions.
- Worked with IT to build data pipelines and analytics tools conducive to enhancing business performance.
- Built analytical tools inside and outside cloud environment (Databricks on AWS) by extracting, transforming
  and integrating large datasets using SQL, R, Python and reporting generated insights through Tableau.
   Achievement: Used R, SQL and Tableau to successfully automate market share calculation and reporting.

### JOHN DEERE, Moline, IL | Data Analyst, Supply Chain

**OCT 2018 - JUN 2019** 

- Managed data aggregation process of web-based tool designed to gain insights on company's supply chain.
- Gathered raw material suppliers' and parts manufacturers' data from internal and external data sources.
- Cleaned and converted collected data into common standards of the business prior to database upload.
- Used SQL and Tableau to automate data extraction and insights generation for various stakeholders.